export const HISTORYA2020 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. All the following are reasons for studying history except that it",
A: "broadens students’ knowledge and understanding.",
B: "helps students to know and understand their heritage.",
C: "improves students ability to assess issues.",
D: "narrows students thinking capacity to only past events.",
answer: "D. narrows students thinking capacity to only past events.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. The European view that Africans had no history before their arrival was",
A: "an understatement.",
B: "a misconception.",
C: "an overstatement.",
D: "a factual conception.",
answer: "B. a misconception.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. The importance of linguistics as a source of history is that it",
A: "helps to trace the origin of animals. . /.",
B: "conforms to tradition.",
C: "helps historians to classify people into ethnic groups.",
D: "discusses the influence of other people.",
answer: "C. helps historians to classify people into ethnic groups.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. All the following are shortcomings of archaeology except that it",
A: "is prone to distortion.",
B: "gives limited account about the objects.",
C: "cannot give absolute chronological account of events.",
D: "is a primary source.",
answer: "D. is a primary source.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. The rise and development of the trans-Saharan trade could be mostly attributed to the",
A: "production of different commodities for batter.",
B: "goldfields of the Western Sudan.",
C: "copper mines of Takedda.",
D: "coming of the Europeans.",
answer: "B. goldfields of the Western Sudan.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. The two dominant ethnic groups in North Africa involved in the trans-Saharan trade were the",
A: "Arabs and Berbers.",
B: "Berbers and Almoravids.",
C: "Almoravids and Tuareg.",
D: "Berbers and Tuareg.",
answer: "A. Arabs and Berbers.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The Eastern trade route of the trans-Saharan trade started from Egypt to",
A: "Gao.",
B: "Hausaland.",
C: "Sijilmasa.",
D: "Timbuctu.",
answer: "B. Hausaland.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. The caravan traders experienced all the following difficulties except",
A: "harassment by the Tuareg.",
B: "attacks by wild animals.",
C: "lack of goods in the trading centres.",
D: "accommodation in the desert.",
answer: "C. lack of goods in the trading centres.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. The two commodities which greatly influenced the trans-Saharan trade were",
A: "gold and silver.",
B: "copper and bronze.",
C: "copper and diamond.",
D: "salt and gold.",
answer: "D. salt and gold.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Prior to the introduction of Islam, the people of West Africa were",
A: "Buddhists.",
B: "Traditionalists.",
C: "Hindus.",
D: "Coptics.",
answer: "B. Traditionalists.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. All the following were factors responsible for the spread of Islam in West Africa except",
A: "Almoravid invasion.",
B: "intermarriages with North Africans.",
C: "trade with Europeans.",
D: "trade with the Berbers.",
answer: "C. trade with Europeans.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Islam penetrated West Africa through",
A: "marriage alliances.",
B: "commercial contacts.",
C: "traditional rulers.",
D: "signing of treaties.",
answer: "B. commercial contacts.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. Which of the following was not an effect of the spread of Islam in West Africa?",
A: "Adoption of Islamic style of dressing",
B: "Introduction of Islamic education",
C: "Adoption of Arabic language in commerce",
D: "Adoption of West Africa customs and traditions",
answer: "D. Adoption of West Africa customs and traditions",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. The introduction of Islam in West Africa enabled many rulers to",
A: "improve their system of administration.",
B: "improve the standard of living of their subjects.",
C: "expand the boundaries of their states.",
D: "abolish the worship of idols in their states.",
answer: "A. improve their system of administration.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Europeans knew about the history of West Africa before the 15th century through",
A: "their contacts with Red Indians.",
B: "the writings of Arab scholars.",
C: "the writings of African historians.",
D: "the writings of European explorers and evangelists.",
answer: "B. the writings of Arab scholars.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. Europeans’ early contact with the people of West Africa was to",
A: "promote African culture.",
B: "find the remains of dead Europeans.",
C: "train the youths for subsistence agriculture.",
D: "establish trade relations.",
answer: "D. establish trade relations.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. Which of the following European groups did not participate in the civilizing mission in West Africa? The",
A: "industrialists.",
B: "explorers.",
C: "traders.",
D: "missionaries.",
answer: "A. industrialists.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. The political objective of European contact with the West Africans was to",
A: "abolish mission schools.",
B: "establish colonies and colonize the people.",
C: "open up trading activities with the people.",
D: "seek for employment in the courts of rulers.",
answer: "B. establish colonies and colonize the people.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. One negative effect of the European contact with West Africa was that it led to",
A: "trade contact between Europeans and West Africans.",
B: "the introduction of the trans-Atlantic slave trade.",
C: "the spread of Christianity.",
D: "the introduction of Western architecture.",
answer: "B. the introduction of the trans-Atlantic slave trade.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. The first stage of the Triangular slave trade witnessed goods being brought to West Africa from",
A: "Asia.",
B: "the Americas.",
C: "the Caribbean.",
D: "Europe.",
answer: "D. Europe.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. The rapid growth of the trans-Atlantic slave trade in West Africa was as a result of",
A: "its profitability to only the Europeans.",
B: "the greatest interest developed by the African religious leaders.",
C: "the availability of able-bodied population in the region.",
D: "the desire of the Americans to have African neighbours.",
answer: "C. the availability of able-bodied population in the region.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. The abolition of the trans-Atlantic slave trade was successful because of the",
A: "availability of slaves.",
B: "introduction of legitimate trade.",
C: "enforcement of international treaties.",
D: "revolts organized by slaves.",
answer: "B. introduction of legitimate trade.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. The judgement which mainly impacted the abolition of the trans-Atlantic slave trade was the",
A: "Assiento of 1713.",
B: "Equipment Treaty.",
C: "Reciprocal Search Treaty.",
D: "Lord Mansfield decision of 1772.",
answer: "D. Lord Mansfield decision of 1772.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. Which of the following factors supported the opposition to the suppression of the trans- Atlantic slave trade?",
A: "Source of wealth for many people",
B: "Parliamentary Act passed in Britain",
C: "Supported by all European powers and merchants",
D: "All local chiefs had become rich from it.",
answer: "A. Source of wealth for many people",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Missionary activities in West Africa had the following impact on the people except",
A: "playing crucial role in the rise of nationalism.",
B: "showing interest in the development of agriculture.",
C: "promoting traditional marriage of more than one wife.",
D: "bringing several regions under European rule.",
answer: "C. promoting traditional marriage of more than one wife.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. The initial objective of missionary activities in West Africa was to",
A: "promote indigenous education.",
B: "convert the people to Christianity.",
C: "promote West African culture.",
D: "improve the standard of living of the people.",
answer: "B. convert the people to Christianity.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. The introduction of Western education in West Africa by the Christian Missions paved the way for the",
A: "eradication of indigenous education.",
B: "training of West African leaders overseas.",
C: "promotion of indigenous education.",
D: "learning of new ideas.",
answer: "D. learning of new ideas.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. One main objective of Christian missionaries’ support for European colonization of West Africa was to",
A: "protect them from hostile ethnic groups.",
B: "promote the development of Western education.",
C: "encourage the growth of local products.",
D: "supplant West African customs.",
answer: "D. supplant West African customs",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. One social impact of the Christian missionary activities on West Africa was",
A: "promotion of agriculture.",
B: "deposition of traditional rulers.",
C: "discouragement of polygamy.",
D: "coronation of African chiefs.",
answer: "C. discouragement of polygamy.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. Which of the following reasons was the main cause of the Scramble for and Partition of West Africa? The",
A: "desire to establish industries in the region.",
B: "desire for raw materials and trade.",
C: "need to train West Africans to manage their resources better.",
D: "need to build schools and churches.",
answer: "B. desire for raw materials and trade.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Which of the following could not be regarded as a positive effect of the Scramble for and Partition of West Africa?",
A: "Establishment of towns and urban centres",
B: "Reduction in ethnic wars and rivalries",
C: "Development of transport and communication",
D: "Killing or deportation of African leaders",
answer: "D. Killing or deportation of African leaders",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. The greatest effect of the Scramble for and Partition of West Africa was the",
A: "establishment of industries.",
B: "construction of roads.",
C: "exploitation of resources.",
D: "establishment of churches. ,",
answer: "C. exploitation of resources.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. The high demand for raw materials in West Africa by the Europeans was due to",
A: "Industrial Revolution.",
B: "high prices of goods.",
C: "durability of the materials.",
D: "abundant production of goods.",
answer: "A. Industrial Revolution.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. The last European nation to join the race for territories in West Africans",
A: "Italy.",
B: "Spain.",
C: "France.",
D: "Germany.",
answer: "A. Italy.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. One achievement of the National Congress of British West Africa (NCBWA) during the colonial period was that it",
A: "enhanced the breakaway of the Africans from churches.",
B: "stimulated a reform in the colonial administration.",
C: "brought about changes in the recruitment of Africans.",
D: "forced many Europeans to resign from the civil service.",
answer: "B. stimulated a reform in the colonial administration.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. In which of the following areas were the colonial masters accused of selective development?",
A: "Building of churches",
B: "Provision of infrastructure",
C: "Building of markets",
D: "Training of soldiers",
answer: "B. Provision of infrastructure",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. The colonial masters used divide and rule tactics in order to",
A: "win the confidence of the educated class.",
B: "share the people’s lands among themselves.",
C: "allow more Europeans to assist in building industries.",
D: "satisfy their desire to subdue the people.",
answer: "D. satisfy their desire to subdue the people.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Mistrust among the people of West Africa at independence could be traced to their",
A: "linguistic differences.",
B: "colonial experience.",
C: "settlement pattern.",
D: "ethnic differences.",
answer: "B. colonial experience.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. The two West African countries which were arbitrarily divided between France and Britain after the defeat of Germany in the first World War were",
A: "Dahomey and Togo.",
B: "Cameroon and Dahomey.",
C: "Togo and Cameroon.",
D: "Dahomey and Ghana.",
answer: "C. Togo and Cameroon.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Some African kings peacefully accepted colonialism because they",
A: "had the support of their people.",
B: "liked the Europeans.",
C: "wanted European support against hostile neighboins.",
D: "lacked popularity among their kinsmen",
answer: "C. wanted European support against hostile neighbours.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. One expectation of nationalists at independence was that",
A: "more roads and railway lines would be built.",
B: "all West Africans would be given European citizenship.",
C: "former colonial masters would train their army.",
D: "all Africans would be given opportunity to study in Europe.",
answer: "A. more roads and railway lines would be built.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. Once independence was achieved West African states expected that",
A: "only the chiefs would be in government.",
B: "traditional institutions would be dismantled.",
C: "all Europeans would surrender their trading firms.",
D: "boundary disputes would no longer be a problem.",
answer: "B. traditional institutions would be dismantled",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. One way neo-colonialism was entrenched in West Africa was by",
A: "sending military aid to West African states.",
B: "exporting European finished goods to West African states.",
C: "holding constitutional conferences in Europe.",
D: "denying the nationalists the chance to study in Europe.",
answer: "B. exporting European finished goods to West African states.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. Which of the following factors was a threat to neo-colonialism in West Africa?",
A: "Population growth",
B: "Pan-Africanism",
C: "Military strength",
D: "Local industries",
answer: "B. Pan-Africanism",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. The Europeans’ attempt to control the new leadership in independent West African states led to",
A: "self reliance.",
B: "regional integration.",
C: "industrial growth.",
D: "neo-colonialism.",
answer: "D. neo-colonialism.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. One problem common to West African states at independence was",
A: "decline in fertility rate.",
B: "rise in infant mortality.",
C: "mistrust among ethnic groups.",
D: "increase of foreign merchants.",
answer: "C. mistrust among ethnic groups.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. The Organization of African Unity failed in some of its activities because it",
A: "lacked effective administrative machinery to enforce its decisions.",
B: "achieved prospect through the establishment of the African Development Bank.",
C: "had been vested with power only to help states achieve independence.",
D: "dealt with border disputes with the help of liberation movements.",
answer: "A. lacked effective administrative machinery to enforce its decisions.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. One major achievement of the Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) was that it",
A: "ended colonial rule.",
B: "encouraged freedom of expression.",
C: "promoted Neo-colonialism.",
D: "maintained peace in West Africa.",
answer: "D. maintained peace in West Africa.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. The body responsible for ensuring peace and cooperation among world nations is the",
A: "North Atlantic Treaty Organization.",
B: "Commonwealth of Nations.",
C: "United Nations Organization.",
D: "Organization of Islamic Cooperation.",
answer: "C. United Nations Organization.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. In what way did West African states benefit from the United Nations Organization?",
A: "Assistance given to freedom fighters",
B: "Participation of West African states in world meetings",
C: "Cultivation of farms to feed its members",
D: "Opening businesses in all member states.",
answer: "B. Participation of West African states in world meetings.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},


]